Merle Montgomery Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Merle Montgomery Papers circa 1904-1983 (bulk 1960-1980)
ML31.M63
Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986
5093 items 18 containers 7.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Merle Montgomery was a music educator, composer, author, editor, administrator, translator, lecturer, and concert pianist. The collection primarily contains business papers and materials related to Montgomery's career and her leadership roles in various music, educational, and arts organizations, including Carl Fischer Inc., Mu Phi Epsilon, National Federation of Music Clubs, and the National Music Council. In addition, the collection includes personal and professional correspondence, biographical materials, photographs, programs, clippings, promotional and publicity materials, and publications.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Hanson, Howard, 1896-1981, ed. Scribner music library.; Kramer, A. Walter (Arthur Walter), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Kramer, A. Walter (Arthur Walter), 1890-1969.; Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986--Archives.; Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986--Correspondence.; Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986--Photographs.; Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986.; Montgomery, Merle, 1904-1986.
Organizations
Carl Fischer Inc.; Eastman School of Music.; International Music Council.; Mu Phi Epsilon.; Musicians Club of New York.; National Federation of Music Clubs.; National Federation of Music Clubs. Junior Division.; National Music Council (U.S.); New York City Opera. Guild.; New York Federation of Music Clubs.; New York Philomusica Chamber Ensemble.; University of Rochester--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Rochester.
Subjects
Arts administrators--United States.; Music in education.; Music patronage--United States.; Music publishers--United States.; Music publishing--United States.; Music--Instruction and study--United States.; Music--International cooperation.; Music--Societies, etc.--United States.; Music--United States--20th century.; Musicians--Photographs.; Women composers--United States.; Women music teachers--United States.
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Newsletters.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Merle Montgomery; 1978
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds the National Music Council Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The Merle Montgomery Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, May 15 Born Merle Campbell, Davidson, Okla.
1924 Married Pleasant Parx Montgomery (died 1929) BFA, Piano, University of Oklahoma, Norman, Okla.
circa 1924 Adopted son Milton
1929-1931 Studied privately with Nadia Boulanger and Isidore Philipp
1929-1933 (Summers) Studied at the American Conservatory of Music, Fontainebleau, France
1931-1933 Extension teacher, Music Theory, University of Oklahoma, Norman, Okla.
1933 Diploma, American Conservatory of Music, Fontainebleau, France
1933-1934 Private teacher, Oklahoma City, Okla.
1934-1938 Head, Piano and Theory, Southwestern Oklahoma College, Weatherford, Okla.
1936 Composed 17 Songs for Children. Chicago, Ill.: Scott Foresman and Co.
1937 M.M., Music Theory, Eastman School of Music, Rochester, N.Y.
1938-1943 Assistant state supervisor and state supervisor, Federal Music Project for Oklahoma
1939 Composed Song for Child for Jack and Jill Magazine Composed 8 Songs for Children
1940 Editor, Oklahoma Music News
1943-1945 Teacher, Piano and Theory, Eastman School of Music, Rochester, N.Y.
circa 1945-1954 Lecturer for Schillinger System of Musical Composition and national educational representative, Carl Fischer Inc., New York, N.Y.
1946-1948 Completed dissertation A Comparative Analysis [and translation] of Vincent D'Indy's "Cours de Composition Musicale" Ph.D., Eastman School of Music, Rochester, N.Y.
1951-1953 President, New York Alumni Chapter of Mu Phi Epsilon
circa 1955 Producer, writer, and host, Let's Go to Musicland! (series of thirteen fifteen-minute films), University of Oklahoma Educational Service Division
1956 Selected Oklahoma Woman of the Year by Soroptimist International of Oklahoma
1956-1966 Assistant manager and educational consultant, Music Department, Oxford University Press, New York, N.Y. Teacher, piano and music theory, Turtle Bay Music School and Westchester Conservatory, N.Y.
1957 Married A. Walter Kramer (died 1969)
circa 1958 Published Music Theory Papers. New York: C. Fischer
1958-1960 President, New York Federation of Music Clubs
1959 Published Music Composition Papers. New York: C. Fischer
circa 1963-circa 1972 Compiler, editor, two volumes in the Scribner Music Library
1964 Named Outstanding Alumna for Distinguished Service, University of Rochester Elected to Trustees' Council of Alumni Advisors, University of Rochester
1964-1966 National vice-president in charge of public relations and governor of Atlantic Province, Mu Phi Epsilon
circa 1965 Charter member, New York City Opera Guild
1967 Received National Citation from Mu Phi Epsilon
1967-1971 Coordinator of symphonic repertoire and vice-president in charge of public relations, Carl Fischer Inc. Manager, Ford Foundation Recording-Publication Program, Carl Fischer Inc.
1971 Founding member, Board of Directors, New York Philomusica Chamber Ensemble
1971-1975 President, National Federation of Music Clubs
1974 Elizabeth Mathias Award from Mu Phi Epsilon
1975-1976 Chairperson, Bicentennial Parade of American Music, National Music Council
1975-1979 President, National Music Council
1976 Inducted into the Oklahoma Hall of Fame
1977 Given Distinguished Service Citation, University of Oklahoma
circa 1977 Vice-president, Musicians Club of New York
1979-1980 Project director, National Black Music Colloquium and Competition
circa 1982 National Federation of Music Clubs representative to the United Nations
1986, Aug. 25 Died, Chantilly, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Merle Montgomery (1904-1986) span the years 1904-1983, with the bulk of the material dating from 1960 to 1980. The papers highlight Montgomery's career and leadership roles in several organizations, programs, and projects in support of music, education and the arts. The collection chronicles her presidencies with the National Federation of Music Clubs from 1971-1975 and the National Music Council from 1975-1979, her career with music publishing firm Carl Fischer Inc., from the mid-1940s to 1971, her management of the Bicentennial Parade of American Music, her scholarly work on the Scribner Music Library, from around 1961 to 1972, and more. There is a small amount of personal material, including correspondence with family and friends, photographs, and biographical documents and clippings. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Biographical Materials, Business Papers, Photographs, Promotional Materials, Programs, Clippings, Publications, and Miscellany.
The Correspondence series, circa 1929-1981, contains professional and personal letters to and from Merle Montgomery relating to her business activities and personal life. The series is divided into two subseries: Professional and Personal. The Professional subseries, 1933-1981, spans her entire career and relates to her activities in music education and publishing, the various music, arts, and cultural organizations, projects, and programs which she led, the mentoring of students and young musicians, and other professional activities. This subseries contains items from the composers Nadia Boulanger, Aaron Copland, Morton Gould, John La Montaine, William Schuman, Louise Talma, and Virgil Thomson. The Personal subseries, circa 1929-1981, includes letters from Montgomery's second husband, A. Walter Kramer, dating from before their marriage up until shortly before his death. There is also correspondence to and from Montgomery's mother, including letters from Merle regarding her studies in Europe in the 1930s. In addition, there are letters from Montgomery's son, her siblings, and numerous friends and extended family.
The Biographical Materials series, 1931-1981, contains a variety of materials by and about Merle Montgomery. There are biographical sketches and press releases from a variety of sources which detail her work history and professional accomplishments. In addition, this series contains biographical sketches of her second husband, A. Walter Kramer. The series also contains clippings about Montgomery and her family, some personal business papers, and several awards and citations that she received. The writings by Montgomery include drafts of speeches and published articles.
The Business Papers series, 1942-1983, is the largest series in the collection. It contains papers relating to Merle Montgomery's career and leadership roles in many local and national organizations, projects, and programs. The series is divided into eleven subseries: Carl Fischer Inc., Ford Foundation Recording-Publication Project, Let's Go to Musicland!, Mu Phi Epsilon, Musicians Club of New York, National Federation of Music Clubs, National Music Council, New York City Opera Guild, New York Philomusica Chamber Ensemble, Scribner Music Library, and University of Rochester.
The Carl Fischer Inc. subseries, 1947-1978, covers both of Montgomery's stints with the music publishing firm and includes correspondence with composers and others concerning various Fischer projects, internal reports and memoranda, publicity and promotional materials, and newsletters. The Ford Foundation Recording-Publication Project, 1966-1972, was a Carl Fischer project which Montgomery continued to manage even after she left Fischer to become president of the National Federation of Music Clubs. This subseries contains correspondence, including a detailed letter to the Ford Foundation discussing the cancellation of the project, applications, and other miscellaneous project papers.
The Let's Go to Musicland! subseries, 1953-1966, relates to a series of thirteen 15-minute films that Montgomery, wrote, produced and hosted for the University of Oklahoma Educational Service Division. The series introduced children to the fundamentals of music and was based on material from her Music Theory Papers. Materials include correspondence detailing the origins and progress of the project, promotional materials, and a partial script.
The Mu Phi Epsilon subseries, circa 1952-1983, contains materials relating to Montgomery's long association with the organization. In addition to national vice-president in charge of public relations and governor of the Atlantic Province, Montgomery was chairman of the board for the Memorial Foundation, editor of Who's Who in MɸE, and president of the New York Alumni chapter. The subseries includes Memorial Foundation documents, promotional items, directories and yearbooks, and reports.
Montgomery was an active member of the Musicians Club of New York, serving as vice president and chairman of the performance committee. The Musicians Club of New York subseries, 1949-1981, contains general materials about the organization as well as correspondence and items which detail Montgomery's activities, such as promoting music in hospitals and old-age homes and supporting young musicians through the Young Artists Awards.
The National Federation of Music Clubs (NFMC) series, 1954-1981, is the largest subseries in the Business Papers series. Montgomery had a thirty-year association with the organization, beginning around 1953 when she was named local chairman of the national convention, up until 1982 when she was NFMC representative to the United Nations. Over the years, she held numerous positions, with the Oklahoma and New York state clubs as well as the national organization. She was president of both the New York Federation of Music Clubs (1958-1960) and the National Federation of Music Clubs (1971-1975). The subseries spans Montgomery's association with the NFMC and includes such documents as correspondence; convention materials; financial documents; meeting agendas, reports and minutes; and publicity and promotional materials. In addition, there are materials documenting particular initiatives, including junior festivals, scholarships, the International Year of the Child, the Parade of American Music, American women composers, Opera for Youth, and the Wolf Trap American University Program for the Performing Arts. This subseries also includes a significant amount of New York Federation of Music Clubs materials.
The National Music Council subseries, 1966-1981, also contains materials relating to the International Music Council. Montgomery was president of the National Music Council from 1975 to 1979 and board chairman and delegate to four International Music Council conventions. Included in this subseries are materials chronicling the Bicentennial Parade of American Music, for which Montgomery was the project manager. This nation-wide project featured concerts at the Kennedy Center showcasing composers from all fifty states, a thirteen-week series of radio programs broadcasting the works of states' composers, and plaques placed at various historical sites relating to American music. In addition, this subseries includes materials about a proposed international festival of music that was being planned by Montgomery and Iain Turpie from 1974 to 1980. There are also internal documents, correspondence, promotional materials, and clippings.
The New York City Opera Guild subseries, 1966-1983, features correspondence, publicity materials, newsletters, and other internal documents such as membership lists and committee meeting minutes. Montgomery was a charter member and vice-president of the New York City Opera Guild.
The New York Philomusica Chamber Ensemble subseries, 1970-1982, relates to the federated chamber ensemble directed by A. Robert Johnson. Montgomery was a member of the founding board of directors in 1971. Materials include internal business papers, promotional and publicity materials, correspondence, and reviews of their concerts.
The Scribner Music Library subseries, circa 1961-1972, contains materials relating to the two volumes that Montgomery edited for the Scribner Music Library series. She compiled and edited Volume One for Beginners and Volume Four, A Century of Piano Music. Volume one contained 207 compositions--of which 186 were original and unpublished at the time--by forty American composers. Volume four featured piano music from the second half of the nineteenth century and the first half of the twentieth century and included sixty-two compositions by forty-seven composers. The subseries contains planning documents, correspondence, drafts and proofs of the copy, reviews, and some publicity materials.
The University of Rochester subseries, 1942-1981, primarily documents Montgomery's alumni activities and membership in the Trustee's Council of Alumni Advisors. It includes alumni papers, internal council documents, correspondence, and materials relating to the Eastman School of Music.
The Photographs series, circa 1904-circa 1980, contains color and black and white photographs, both candid and posed, of Merle Montgomery alone and with colleagues and family. Most of the photographs were taken during Montgomery's later years and show her at various parties and professional functions. There are also a few family pictures and some publicity shots of Montgomery. In addition, this series includes several publicity shots of musicians and performers.
The Promotional Materials series, circa 1960-circa 1980, contains promotional and publicity material, such as brochures, pamphlets, and informational literature, on various music, educational, arts, and cultural organizations and programs. These materials span Montgomery's career and reflect her interests and her many professional and personal activities. This series also contains publicity and promotional materials on musicians, performers, composers and conductors, many of whom Montgomery promoted through her professional organizations. These materials may also include photographs and correspondence.
The Programs series, 1931, circa 1960-circa 1980, contains programs for various music and cultural performances and events. Many of these programs describe events that were produced or sponsored by organizations in which Montgomery was involved.
The Clippings series, circa 1960-circa 1980, contains newspaper and magazine clippings about topics, organizations, programs, and people related to Merle Montgomery's professional life and interests. Many clippings are taken from official publications belonging to organizations in which Montgomery was actively involved.
The Publications series, 1956-1981, contains a small amount of music, educational, cultural, and arts publications that relate to Montgomery's professional interests.
The Miscellany series, circa 1956-1981, contains various items, including speeches (by others), complete and partial narratives (unidentified) (draft and final), articles, brochures, catalogs, librettos, and materials on education.
Organization of the Merle Montgomery Papers
The Merle Montgomery Papers are organized in nine series:
Correspondence, circa 1929-1981
Biographical Materials, 1931-1981
Business Papers, 1942-1983
Photographs, circa 1904-circa 1980
Promotional Materials, circa 1960-circa 1980
Programs, 1931, circa 1960-circa 1980
Clippings, circa 1960-circa 1980
Publications, 1956-1981
Miscellany, circa 1956-1981
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011570500
Container List
- Correspondence, circa 1929-1981 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence to and from colleagues, associates, friends, family members, businesses, and organizations relating to professional and personal activities. Includes telegrams, postcards, greeting cards, invitations, and announcements. Some correspondence has accompanying material.
  - Professional, 1933-1981 (Box 1)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization.
    - A-B (Box-folder 1/1)
    - C-D (Box-folder 1/2)
    - E-G (Box-folder 1/3)
    - H-K (Box-folder 1/4)
    - L-R (Box-folder 1/5)
    - S-T (Box-folder 1/6)
    - U-Z (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Personal, circa 1929-1981 (Box 1-2)
    - Letters from Merle Montgomery, 1929-1971 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Letters from Merle Montgomery, undated, (2 folders) (Box-folder 1/9-10)
    - Letters from A. Walter Kramer, 1951-1971, Includes two items written by Merle Montgomery to Kramer and a 1971 letter to M. Montgomery from Kramer's music publisher. (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Letters from A. Walter Kramer, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Family, 1929-1931, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Family, 1957-1972, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Family, undated (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Unidentified family and friends, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Unidentified family and friends, 1948, undated (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Unidentified family and friends, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Unidentified family and friends, 1935-1981, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Miscellaneous family, 1957-1972, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
- Biographical Materials, 1931-1981 (Box 2-3)
  Clippings, biographical sketches, resumés, press releases, correspondence, personal business papers, awards, citations, writings, items about spouse A. Walter Kramer and other family members, programs, and Montgomery's passport.
  - Biographies, 1941-1971, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Clippings, 1948-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box-folder 2/10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1975 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - A. Walter Kramer materials (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Awards and citations, 1943-1981, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Business papers, 1965-1980 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Family materials, 1931-1980 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Writings (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Miscellany, (2 folders) (Box-folder 3/5-6)
- Business Papers, 1942-1983 (Box 3-14)
  Correspondence, agendas, reports, meeting minutes, memos, convention programs, financial documents, brochures, publicity and promotional materials, by-laws, membership lists, newsletters, articles, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by organization or program.
  - Carl Fischer Inc., 1947-1978 (Box 3-4)
    Newsletters, publicity materials, news releases, announcements, programs, invitations, brochures, catalogs, memoranda, clippings, correspondence, rental and pricing lists, financial papers, company histories, reports, drafts, and miscellaneous project documents.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of materials and chronologically therein.
    - Brochures and catalogs (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1978, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Financial papers, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Memoranda, 1966-1971, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
    - News releases, 1957-1971, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Newsletters, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Rental lists (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Reports, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Schillinger material, 1947-1964 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Ford Foundation Recording-Publication Project, 1966-1972 (Box 4-5)
    Correspondence, lists of composers and musical pieces, price lists, narratives about composers and musical pieces, application forms, miscellaneous project papers.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of materials.
    - Application forms (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Narratives (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Let's Go to Musicland! 1953-1966 (Box 5)
    Scripts, outlines, continuities, drafts of scripts, promotional materials, correspondence, clippings, planning documents, negatives.
    - Correspondence, 1953-1966 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Planning documents (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Promotional materials (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Release forms (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Scripts (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Mu Phi Epsilon, circa 1952-1983 (Box 5-6)
    Correspondence, reports, directories, procedural rules, brochures, newsletters, member lists, promotional materials, clippings, programs, leaflets.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Directories, brochures, yearbooks, 1952-1983 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Memorial Foundation document, 1978 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - New York World's Fair documents, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Newsletters, 1960, 1972, 1980 (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Programs, 1953-1981, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Reports, 1953-1982 (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Resumé material, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Miscellaneous papers, (2 folders) (Box-folder 6/2-3)
  - Musicians Club of New York, 1949-1981 (Box 6)
    Correspondence, reports, by-laws, meeting minutes, brochures, newsletters, member lists, promotional and publicity materials, programs, certificate of incorporation.
    - Correspondence, 1968-1977 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Promotional materials, 1964-1981 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Miscellaneous documents, 1949-1978 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - National Federation of Music Clubs, 1954-1981 (Box 6-10)
    Correspondence, by-laws, convention materials, financial documents, memoranda, applications, meeting agendas, reports, minutes, publicity and promotional materials, reviews, newsletters, programs, articles, clippings.